hello and welcome to
the active inference lab to our first
ever
applied active inference symposium today
it's june
21st 2021 and we're very honored to be
here with professor
carl fristen and many of our lab
participants
just as a way of quick introduction the
active inference lab
is a non-profit organization that is a
participatory
open science laboratory and we're
working to curate and develop
applications related to the active
inference framework
something that hopefully we'll be going
into a lot more in detail today and this
is
a screenshot of our website
as far as the overview of this symposium
there are three organizational units in
the lab
edu education dot coms communication
and dot tools and each of these
units are going to facilitate a 45
minute or so
session and we'll have a short break in
between
sessions so in our weekly meetings over
the past weeks
for each organizational unit we've been
developing
questions and getting excited about
things that we wanted to
talk to you about
as far as a few overarching themes that
were kind of spoken to um
really through the whole journey of our
lab but also across
organizational units the first theme is
applying active inference across systems
again something that will come up
probably in all sections
the idea of research debt the idea that
we don't want to
be developing um research frameworks
that have a huge burden on those who are
learning and applying
and that especially early in the
formalization of frameworks
it's extremely valuable to increase the
accessibility
so that we don't end up with major
headaches and incompatibilities
later on collective intelligence and
the ways in which that is manifest
across different systems
transdisciplinary teams projects and
communities which are kind of like
nested levels of organization
but transdisciplinarity is something
that is
necessary for the type of work that
we're all interested in
and also just modern challenges and
opportunities for research
and all that that means related to
online and everything else and
of course anything else that you have
tumbling around and
wanted to bring to the table
thematically so
there we are with our sort of lab
overview and introduction
let's go to our first organizational
unit.edu
the goal of edu is to
scaffold and create a participatory and
dynamic
active inference body of knowledge which
we'll talk more about in a second
and our progress and actions this year
have been to release a terms list v1
which
benefited greatly from your feedback and
also we're now
updating the terms list to version 2
which now includes five complete
language translations
and many references and citations
for the terms
the way that we're approaching the
development of the terms
is by using approaches that
place ontology and progressively more
formalized versions
of ontologies as kind of the backbone of
an educational
body of knowledge so we started on the
left side here with a terms list
in the first quarter of 2021 and the
ontology working group
is like a train that's pushing to the
right as they're learning ontology by
doing
and developing progressively stronger
and stronger
ways of relating the terms and the
concepts
that are essential for understanding
active inference
and this will help us develop principled
educational material that's also able to
be
translated rapidly
alex do you want to give a quick thought
on where knowledge engineering comes
into play
yeah thanks um at this slide
we are showing this work with anthology
with system engineering approach which
we are also using
in the lab and considering possible
deliverables of working on educational
materials and creating them
we should have at some point of time
textbooks and educational courses
and actually maybe this lab is started
from the idea that
textbook for active influence should be
created
also we see some connection that can be
applied to
organizational management for creating
translations to make it
multi-language from the beginning
and also we should see for
some domain specific use cases that we
can
understand in terms of wet ontology
what we are going to create
thanks alex so on to the
questions section we're going to start
off pretty
broad here in the edu how do we go about
determining the core ideas and terms
for active inference
this will be the format of the question
slides carl
so feel free to jump in
right
i guess um it will be structured around
the um the
key ideas um and
essentially ingredients that underwrite
the um
the free energy principle and how that
translates
into active inference so you know
without thinking about it too deeply
my mind just goes to what are the things
what are the basic ingredients
you need to explain to somebody and
what active inference is and and why it
works
and it normally starts off with the
notion of a generative model
and then from that um you spin off um
all the appropriate um mathematical
ideas and constructs and descriptions
that would
would attend that um i mean it may be
best to
um reflect the question back to you so
this is a really neat idea having an
ontology
and it's certainly my experience that
people
are entertained by um sometimes the
poetic use of
phrases and descriptions such as um
epistemic reforms
when trying to grapple with you know
what what
are the fundamental ideas behind active
inference
some of them are fundamental and some of
them are not so it's so
it's certainly an interesting idea to
try and tie down the ontology
but let me let me ask you
just means what it says in the sense
that you're
trying to define the essential concepts
and how they relate to each other is
that is that the basic idea
yep going back to this slide here
we want to have a continuum
from a list of terms potentially that
could be developed into
coherent and again principled course
material
and competencies but also develop
a logic and we're developing within the
sumo
ontology development framework which
defines
not just relational edges but actually
uh actual logic
and so we hope to be able to ask like is
this a complete active inference model
have we really checked off all the boxes
and used those kinds of logical tools
that are accessible to the
well-developed ontological frameworks
okay well that's very compelling and um
very clear um it strikes me then that
you
you know it would be useful to link that
operational ontology
to the underlying maths so you're much
of the
much of the conceptual steps both in
understanding and
implementing um active inference
usually in terms of simulating your
interesting behavior or
um using it as an observation model to
explain some empirical
uh data from from a study much of it
um can be developed in terms of a series
of
moves um that usually
or in fact almost universally are
inherit from the
are framed in terms of
[Music]
either information theory or linear
algebra
or differential equations and you can
just build the story from that so
um if you're looking for that degree of
formal and useful um uh
detail um then it would be
one principle you might refer to is
basically what your
where does one equality assertion or
description
or variable or object
where does it come from in terms of
inheriting from the the more basic
formula
so what i'm thinking of here is
where does active inference start and
how do you get to
the calculus and the bayesian mechanics
that you would you
you'd associate with with active
inference and my guess is
given the structure or the way that you
have
uh approached the ontology you've
probably actually done that already or
are in the process of doing that are you
going to go through some examples
that would sort of highlight the you
know the strategy and the
um and the problems which are usually
more illuminating than
the solutions that you've encountered so
far
sure i'll switch here to this screenshot
of
the the current state of what it looks
like and
we're starting just in tabular form
by compiling up to five references and
citable definitions
first just looking for exact cases where
a term
is used and then we'll go from how the
term has been used
towards synthetic definitions that
capture different senses of the term
and then along with the concise
narrative of the field
and also ontology experts who are
here with us we're going to then be
working
to make the actual logical underpinnings
elucidated in terms of specifiable code
rather than just concise english
definitions and then from that
sort of generator of the formal
relationships will be able to
descend into mathematical formalisms or
other
natural human languages yeah
well we'll keep you posted on this
project though
for sure let's go to this next question
and
imagine that we had that set of
terms in development it's going to be a
work in progress our whole lives
how would we go from core terms and
ideas
to an interactive and enlivening
education
that speaks to people from many
different backgrounds
so i i'm going to answer this question
from the point of view of my experience
as a supervisor which is probably a
little bit of narrow of a narrow remit
from
your more general ambition uh and i
imagine that this
is uh related to this notion of was it
sort of
debt i can't remember now but this
notion that you don't want to put too
much
pressure on people um when becoming
acquainted
with the utility and application of um
of either the code or all the ideas so
um in my experience with um in an
academic setting
uh just having toy simulations is
usually the best way to give people
a feel for what these uh
what this approach does and how it can
be used so
um it's you're enormously potent in
terms of demystifying
and also illustrating the functionality
at hand or that can be accessed
um it also
having a sort of um you know a working
um working or at least a toy model
um sort of provides a proof of principle
and that can um strip away the magic as
well
and i think your your
your ambition to try and make this
accessible to people who are not
necessarily fluent in the underlying
information theory or dynamical systems
it
is is very laudable and perfectly
feasible
so again in my experience some of the
most
creative applications of active
inference
are can be by people who don't really
necessarily wonder too much what's
underneath the hood
it all comes back again to the design of
the generative model
so if you get the if you get the
generative model right
um and it's apt to describe the
thing that you want to understand or to
simulate
um then usually everything else follows
uh
follows suit and i mean that in the
sense that you can just take off the
shelf
software which i presume that you your
ultimate ambition is to make available
um and make it work in the service of so
say well what would this
agent or this synthetic creature
or person um do in exchange
with um her environment if
this was the generative model and this
was the genetic process
so a lot of this um a lot of this
really i imagine in terms of answering
your question how do we go from core
terms to interactive and enlightening
education
is just establishing a language
a lexicon that allows you to talk
through
somebody in constructing their own
um simulations that speak to the issues
that engage them
um either academically or be uh or
beyond
academia um so
um clearly then the core terms play the
role of
uh literally a language in terms of
communication which brings us back again
to
the you know the importance of the
ontology um and having
the terms um linked in a formal way
to the uh the
the mathematical expressions and also
procedures and processes
um you know so i guess that
a precondition to do the uh to use the
core terms
in an interactive and enlivening
educative sense
will rest upon getting that and getting
that ontology right
in my experience you know the best way
to get the ontology right
in the sense of it being enabling
um is just to talk about the terms and
until everybody
until there's some consensus and
everybody understands them
in terms of either their tediology well
so i know
in both in terms of their technology but
also
in terms of where they come from from
the point of view of the code
and ultimately the maths underwrites all
this
is that the sort of um answer you're
looking for here
or thinking along with are you thinking
along the same lines
it sounds great there's so many
dimensions there
just to provide a summary or just jump
in
at one place what is active inference
and what does active inference do
right so that's perfect because i was
just thinking it would be
really useful just to go down the sort
of the the terms that you had in the
um in the um previous but one slide
highlighted in green because i think
you know all the heavy lifting here is
is really just shouting about
um what what are the core
um aspects and claims
or um the thing the core things that
you're trying to communicate with
any one of those terms so for me active
inference
would be a description
of a process
that can be seen as
something that arises from the free
energy principle so you can either
tell that story from the point of view
of a physicist
and say that active inference
is a technological description of
processes that systems that
self-organize
must possess or you could tell the story
or
define active infants from the point of
view of neurobiology and histology
um you know from a point of view say
predictive processing
and describes what what it entails um
and i've used the word basic mechanics
before because
um from the point of view you know the
physics definition
it would be um a teleological
description of a bayesian mechanics that
necessarily arises
um with some certain with certain
assumptions from any self-organizing
system
um one key thing about
active inference which um
i think would be important to put in the
definition in the ontology i'm not sure
it's it's already there but you know
if you're in charge of sculpting the
ontology
um then you're in the position to make
sure it's there um
is it it it's about
uh it's beyond predictive um processing
it's beyond sentience and it emphasizes
um or reflects the
pragmatic term at the beginning of this
century really
um sort of epitomized by the sort of the
four e's
you know embodied um
extended and the like um to make it
clear that sentience is
is active and that you are talking about
your
um the circular causality of engagement
of any
um particle personal plant with whatever
is out there so that would be
certainly one thing um to emphasize in
terms of the
your what active inference means the
inference is interesting in the sense
that it
does imply a process
and a process with purpose which is to
infer
which is why i keep using the word the
other
description of something that's actually
underneath the hood from the point of
view of
physics one final point here
is um there's an easy confusion i think
between first of all active inference
and passive inference so that's
certainly something
which probably needs resolving certainly
in the philosophical literature so i
often come across
um the you know philosophers
who say well there's passive influence
or perceptual imprints
which is just basically inferring
uh states of affairs in the world um
on the basis of some sensory evidence
and then there's the extra bit which is
the active bit which is now you're in
charge of
gathering that sensory evidence upon
which you are now
going to um prosecute your perceptual
inference
that that that's an interesting
dichotomy which i'm not sure
is you know um is the right is
a correct um dichotomy um
um if it's not right i'm not sure that
it is not right
in the sense that it is a useful
distinction
but certainly is not what active
inference was originally um
um termed to mean you know
by conjoining active and inference there
were a number of motivations first it
was a generalization of david mccain's
active learning um but
probably um more importantly it was
it was a nod to the notion of active
sensing
an active and your active perception
that
perception is in and of itself and
an active process a constructive process
that you have to put
policies plans and action into the game
so that i think would be one
important um aspect of active inference
to
to define and i don't know that it has
been defined so far so
you know perhaps it's your job to to
define that the other thing which is
um important i think in terms
of emphasizing what
active inference entails actually comes
from
that inactive perspective which is
inference
about the consequences of action
and that has an important but really
simple
um concomitant
that the consequences of action are in
the future
and that means you now have to think if
you're thinking from
about active inference um in terms of
of teneology or as a normative
um theory of of behavior of sentient
behavior
and you have to now think about i'm
sorry and i should say
uh qualify when i say normative i mean
it can be operationally defined in terms
of
as an optimization process that in turn
requires you to define the objective
function
or functional and that's important
practically because if you're now
thinking
about sentient behavior active inference
and it's influence about things that not
haven't yet happened
because you haven't yet acted um then
you're necessarily talking about
objective functions or functionals that
are about
states of affairs in the future and that
is an important
move um and something that active
inference embraces
which goes beyond predictive coding so
much of the literature in the 20th
year in the 1990s you know
and subsequent much of the literature
that
inspired that sort of inactive
perception or active sensing
take situated cognition um take on
um on sentience um
originated in your in things like
predictive coding
but predictive coding is not what is
meant by
active inference you can do predictive
coding just by um
if you're a statistician just minimizing
variational free energy
um that that that's only um
half the game once you move into the
world of active inference
from a technological perspective all
your
you are you have to do that you have to
um form beliefs about hidden states of
affairs
in the world um using sort of the
perceptual side of perceptual inference
but that is only in the service of
rolling out into the future
um and deciding what the best thing is
to do next and that running out into the
future
and deciding clearly calls for an
objective function
so in active inference that would be the
expected free energy which may or may
not be unfortunately named but that's
that's what it is um
and therefore active inference sort of
implies that you are committed to
optimizing an expected free energy and
implicitly it's all about choosing the
next
thing to do so for me those would be two
would be two sort of cardinal things
that should be embraced by definition of
active inference
that you know transcend other normative
approaches so for example you know
reinforcement learning in behavioral
psychology
um would be all about what the good
things are to do and you commit to a
loss functionality
value function of states um your if that
was
your um the kind of behavior that you're
trying to describe
if on the other hand you were all about
the psychophysics of perception or just
building
base or digit or terrorist recognition
systems
where you weren't in charge of gathering
those data then your objective functions
will be
would be very very different um but what
active infant says well you can't you
can't
carve up the two problem domains because
they're just both
of the same coin and thereby you're you
know
you're now facing the problem of
defining an objective function
that is fit for purpose that does both
um
the belief updating about latent states
or hidden
states generating the data and also
the best way to
solicit solicit or cause those data or
outcomes
under some prior preferences or some
goal-directed
constraints is that a good
long-winded answer thank you for the
comprehensive answer
it leads directly to our next questions
which are
what is the free energy principle and
especially
what is the relationship between active
inference and the free energy
principle
right well that's that's i think a
slightly
easier question to to to answer and the
free energy principle
um is um just a variational principle of
least action
um it um why is it
special or not
formally identical to all the other
variational principles that we use
if you look under the hood right from
quantum through statistical and
stochastic
um to classical mechanics well
the only thing that differentiates
really the variational
uh principle of least action that is the
uh or that is the free energy principle
is that you're paying careful attention
to the separation of states to which you
apply that principle
um the separation of states into the
states of
a an agent or a particle or a part of a
person and and the outside states so
technically if you were in
statistical thermodynamics for example
you'd normally assume
that separation in terms of some
idealized gas that was contained within
the container or
heat reservoir or a heat bath without
really worrying about where the heat
bath or the
the heat reservoir came from but the
free energy principle
says well noah you can't really do that
you've really got to attend very
carefully to
to what um license is a separation of
different kinds of states so you can
assign to the inside of something on the
outside of something
and the states that mediate the exchange
between the inside the outside
outside and then you get into the markov
blanket and mark off boundary
literature so just to summarize a free
energy principle is just
a a principle of least action
by which i mean that there is a
description of dynamics in terms of the
most likely paths
any system will take that is
the special provenance of um
a partitioning or a separation of the
states of some
universe into the states that are owned
by an
agent or a particle and those that are
not and
the states that mediate the exchange
between them
so that would be the free energy
principle um active imprints as i say is
a sort of um
technological spin-off from um
the the free energy principle in the
sense that
um in the same sense that you have
now at hand a principle of least
action um you know that it
allows you to identify
simulate define the paths or
trajectories or the narratives
that a system the most likely paths
trajectories or narratives
that a system will pursue under certain
conditions and those conditions are just
that there is an attracting set of
states
um to which that system um
will converge to
or will look as if it's attracted to
um so sorry what i was
working towards was the notion of um
an attracting set as a metaphor for
equipping that physics
with a tediology and that tediology is
nicely illustrated by the notion of
attraction
so you know when mathematicians talk
about attractors
in the uh particular case in the free
energy principle these are these
sort of pullback protractors or the kind
of attractors that you get
in random dynamical systems um
there's a a proper and natural tendency
to think that these
particular states um of the attracting
set
literally attract in the sense of you
know
um gravitational attraction
or any other kind of attraction they
pull
um
they pull states towards them so that to
me would be
a technological uh interpretation which
i think is much closer to active
inference that you're saying that
influence is a process that has a
purpose and
the underlying free energy principle
looks
uh allows you to say the way it looks as
if self-organizing systems
uh show these certain properties they're
attracted
to certain states they show um
they're attracted to certain paths and
we can describe those
in terms of the theological ontology
and that would be active inference um
one practical difference between
active inference and the free energy
principle is that the free energy
principle is just a principle
it's neither right or wrong it's just
like um um
[Music]
millage is uh noted it's like sort of
know this theorem
or your um or hamilton's principle of
least action
um but as soon as you start to say well
i think that this
principle applies to this population or
person or particle
and that certainly recommits you or
requires you to define
a um the the attracting
set of states a pullback attractor um in
another
jargon the equivalent would be a
generative model and as soon as you
commit to a genetic model
to explain the technology of this system
or this agent
or this person and then you've moved
into the world of non-falsifiable
principles into falsifiable hypotheses
because you could have chosen the wrong
charity moral
and thereby there will be evidence for
choosing this
generator model or that generative model
so
the relationship between active imprints
and the free energy principle is
operationally quite simple
you know active inference is the
application of the free energy principle
to a particular system
but in that application you're bringing
a lot of tediology to the table
and more specifically um
having you're having to commit to a
particular generative model
and as soon as you do that that becomes
your theory or your hypothesis about
what is an app description
for this system so a number of i think
sort of interesting distinctions
in terms of the relationship between
active inference and free energy
principle
that i imagine um your ontology is
already addressed or
it certainly is certainly addressing
well we'll get there thank you for that
excellent answer
for the next question lorena please read
it out
oh hi so still in the spirit of
broad questions and broad terms uh and
that i think
comes in line came before so how and
where
does the idea of information play a role
in the free energy principle
and how does it relate or is active
inference
in the sense what is something to keep
in mind
when thinking about information dynamics
in active inference
right bill these are great questions i'm
getting the hang of this now you just
want me to talk
i've presented a question to another
talking
which is which i'm very happy to do um
are you sure you want me to do that or
should this be a conversation perhaps
it'll turn into a conversation at some
point
anyway so information so
it plays um a dual role um
um in the sense that
information theoretic formulations
underpin most of the derivations behind
that principle of least action
and and it can be no other way in the
sense that all mechanics
from physics is really articulated in
terms of probability densities or
distributions
um and as soon as you um
have a mechanics that is um or a
calculus or probability distributions
you're effectively
in the world of information theory and
you see that at many different
um levels so one nice example of this
is that the the central um
quantity that we often use
to score the likelihood of being in a
particular state
um if you're a statistician that would
be the marginal likelihood
if you you know were fluent um
with with an fep ontology it would be
surprising
uh almost simply a surprise and if
that is just basically the
self-information it's um if you're a
physicist you look at this as a
potential it's a negative log
probability
so you you start really um
when thinking about the physics with
this um central concept of
self-information which
the iep can be read as a potential
function
or a surprisal function or surprise and
it is the thing that the
variational free energy is a bound
approximation too
so that level and then everything else
every other move you make mathematically
in terms of
[Music]
the expected self-information being the
entropy
and you know why that is important as a
characterization of various probability
distributions
in the setting of self-organization um
and you know would testify to the fact
that information theory is absolutely
central to all the maths that underlies
the the physics of the sentience that
emerges
from um having a distinction between the
states of the system
and states that are not in the system
namely the markov blanket
having said that i think information
um to most people's minds
um usually means more certainly
in the folk psychology context it's
really
information about something um and
the um fep active implants has i think
something quite special to the bring to
the table here that
goes beyond um information theoretic
treatments
of uh you know that you get in
communication and signal processing
and rate distortion theorems all of that
kind of information
is just um your extensions of
information theory that inherit from
self-information or the implausibility
of a particular event
or message
you know or in your more abstract
domains such as
sentence and consciousness you would go
to something like integrated information
theory
but that is all about this
um shannon-esque kind of information the
opposite the other kind of information
which is
information about something so what i
wanted
to try and uh put on the table is the
very fact
that you've got this markov blanket or
separation of
and states on the inside and states on
the outside
means that now you can equip the states
on the inside with the role
of encoding posterior conditional
bayesian beliefs about states on the
outside
and that introduces technically
a different kind of information geometry
a different kind of information theory
where crucially now you can read the
internal dynamics
as um containing or having information
about what's going on on the outside and
this is a really important move
equipping your neural dynamics or
variational message passing or belief
propagation in a computer
with an information geometry that now
allows you to read off
the state of the computer or the state
of the neural activity
in terms of what it is encoding
or belief or the information it contains
about
the outside and so that that that sort
of
dual aspect information geometry has
been celebrated
to a minor extent in the philosophy
literature by vanya
um vice um you know
asking the question is you know is this
really the maths
of sentience where you now have
information
about things and in a sense that you
know that really is the heart of the
free energy principle in the sense
or active inference anyway in the sense
that it equips
um that jewel that information geometry
i mean technically what you are saying
is that
any particular internal state of a
computer or a person
or a brain now can be read
as encoding a bayesian or a posterior
belief
about um other states namely hidden or
latent causes
outside the markov blanket and that
defines
technically something called a
statistical manifold and as soon as
there is
a statistical manifold there's an
information geometry
and any movement on that manifold
necessarily implies a change in your
bayesian beliefs namely bayesian belief
updating which means now there's
a an interpretation of neuronal dynamics
movements on a statistical manifold on
the inside
in terms of belief updating so
the the notion of active inference as
the process of belief updating
really um you know rests upon this
fundamental notion that there's
information about stuff going on um
about stuff
that is encoded or parameterized
by the by the internal machinations
and the mechanics and the dynamics of of
the inside
so i think it might be quite important
to if you're trying to describe or
educate um people in terms of
how they should understand information
um
as playing a central role in sentience i
think it'd be important to differentiate
between
the um the mathematical notions of
shannon information and self-information
and the countless of probability
and mutual information for example and
say that this is not the kind of
information that is implicit
in an information geometry and the
sentence that is
afforded by active inference when now
you're understanding neuronal dynamics
or
message passing in the computer on on
some um
on some sort of factor graph
and uh because in this instance
each of those messages or that those
neural dynamics
um can now be read as belief updating
namely changing your mind
about other things
so that the stuff on the inside has
information
about stuff on the outside
thanks for this important answer and
we're going to
pass over a few questions and go to
18 with stephen reading the question to
continue on this theme about the
separation
of the inside and the outside so
thank you stephen and please read off
18.
thank you um it's going to ask how can
the integrity
of the active inference process theory
be maintained when blankets blanket
states and generative models
are being interpreted in novel ways so
we were thinking about um what do you
think
of discussions around markov or pearl
fristen blankets etc
all right that's an excellent question i
mean i have a quite a technical answer
um so if it's getting too technical tell
me
i'll try and get back to what you know
um what you what you um
we're really trying to unearth um so
this is not a fast moving field but
certainly been
a a delicate and important um area of
discussion over the past few years
so in the original introduction of
markov blankets there was
um an explicit nod to
um pearl's construction of markov
blankets and how rock of blankets are
used practically in terms of
simplifying message passing in
in computer science however
that may have been um something of an
oversimplification
and because the from the point of view
of the free energy principle
um it is um the the kind of causality
that the uh the free energy principle
deals with
is not the kind of causality that
um people particularly people like pearl
but also
people dealing with things like granger
causality um
deal with um so we're not
from the point of view of the free
energy principle that starts
with um a
stochastic differential equation or a
random dynamical
system written as a random dynamical
equation
and ou processes being simple examples
uh in physics these would be linger like
equations
common to all of these starting points
is time and evolution and dynamics
now there is nothing in pearl's
formulations
well certainly there's nothing in
pearl's book on causality that deals
with time
um and i know that because i uh before
the days of pdfs and
being able to go and search particular
words i had to go through and find out
there's one paragraph that mentions
dynamics
um so you know if you were in in
statistics computer science
you know these this will be the world of
dynamic bayesian nets
um the the the is their take on
something which is actually much more
universal which is basically
um the universe as a markovian dynamical
process
so just stepping back
the the challenge now
is to articulate
um independence independences
that underwrite markov blankets in the
sense of pearl
in terms of dynamics so you've now got
to
link two quite distinct fields
which is basically the fields of
dynamics and launch van processes
and things that have paths of least
action
to the world of statistics and
pearl-esque independences
and causality as interventions that have
observable consequences the problem in
doing that linking is that you have to
um really abandon the notion of
causality
in the world of range of causality in
pearl because
causality is baked into an inherent in
writing down
any um differential equation
be it stochastic or random or
deterministic in the sense that states
cause motion
so the causality in this context would
be a more control
theoretic causality so that means that
you can't then use the causality concept
later on but it does mean that you've
now got to
derive from a dynamical markovian
calculus um the um
the necessary um conditions
that would lead to um the conditional
independences that are necessary to
define markov boundaries
um just to slip in here um the markov
blanket
um is um if you
is composed of minimal blankets mainly
boundaries in the sense of pearl and on
most recent analyses it
it looks as if the blanket is actually
two markov boundaries
um in the sense of pearl but to get
to the sense of pearl you've got to
think very carefully
about what are the constraints that
lead to the
the conditional independences where
those constraints are specified in terms
of equations of motion
um and um you know
and things like the amplitude of random
fluctuations
so once you've um once you've
seen that that is the link that needs to
be made
that actually um simplifies the thing
it simplifies things in the sense
there's no real attitude for
interpretation
so i'm going back to your the part of
your question you know
blankets and genitive models are being
interpreted in novel ways
and i i don't think there's any latitude
of
any novel interpretation other than the
um
sorry if in novel ways you mean the best
way
or the correct way and we just haven't
got that yet then i would
you know i'd concur entirely with that
if you think that there is some
latitude there's some library of uh
insightful reinterpretations and
redefinitions
uh all of which have equal veracity then
i i would suggest that's not the case
there's
only one way and there's only one markov
blanket
um or there's only one particular
partition um
that will give you that can be
articulated in terms of
markov blankets and the only novelness
there is really in tying down very
precisely and um
and defensibly how you get from
a longevan formulation to
a markov blanket um at the moment the
novel way of doing that
um looks as if it's a
[Music]
that the conditional independence is a
rise from sparse dynamical coupling of
causal coupling
so if you read um the
the causality as the
influence that a state has on the motion
of itself or any other state
in this sort of minimal launch run like
uh description of the universe um
then it is the sparsity of influence on
the sparsity of coupling
that leads to conditional independences
and if the system has a sufficiently
rich
sparsity of conditional independences
and implicitly coupling
then it will have a particular petition
and if it has that particular
petition then the then the free energy
principle holds
so i think the discussions around markov
pearl
fristen and blankets are essential
they're fascinating
and the conclusions of those discussions
that i think are gonna
probably um have to refer back to the
underlying maths and that
maths is all about connecting linger
formulations of physics to the kind
of calculus that pearl
um has established um you know in
a more statistical sense
thank you for the educational answer
this brings us almost to
the end of the dot edu section so i will
pass to the final question to be read by
dean who had several excellent points
and questions
so dean feel free to ask however
you would like uh
good morning uh so the question is
what's the difference between a subject
matter expert
and a prediction prediction matter
expert and how does this relate
to your mode of interaction
you're going to have to unpack what
subject and prediction matter experts
means for me yeah so
for me interesting you become a subject
matter expert by gaining a certain
amount of concentration in a
in a particular field or area and you
become a prediction matter expert when
you are able to
think more distributively more
dispersively
and so i think what when i read
some of the things and listen to some of
the stuff that i've heard you
talk about you you've brought these two
worlds
together and so i'm kind of interested
in
in hearing what you think in terms of
introducing some of the the ideas and
principles that you brought
into a world where traditionally we
focused on
concentrating whether it's materializing
something
from an engineering perspective or
deciding what's in and what's out
you've brought in another aspect to look
at and i'm i'm just curious what you
think of that
okay that's a fascinating um distinction
i'm not sure it's terribly important
when i think about it because clearly
you're the expert on this but
it certainly would be fascinating to
consider
the conditions under which you were able
to simulate the emergence
of a subject matter versus a prediction
matter expert in silicon for example
just as a proof of principle that these
are both um
effectively based optimal ways of
responding to a particular environment
and my guess is that you you would
be able to do that relatively easily
by appealing to the ideas that you find
in
[Music]
applying some of active inference
notions to
structure learning and development
where the basic idea is if you've got
a very volatile environment by which
i mean that there are there's lots of
uncertainty
in the contingencies or possibly there
are lots of random fluctuations
um that are irreducible in terms of your
your ability to
to predict the the outcome of the
trajectory
of latent states of the world in which
you are becoming an expert
then you um when you parameterize
your uncertainty you're usually
formally in terms of the precision of
various likelihood mappings or
probability transition um matrices in a
sort of discrete state space generative
models
when you parameterize your beliefs about
that
that uncertainty um irreducible
uncertainty
and volatility then
agents that believe or have inferred
that they are in a very volatile
changeable capricious world
usually become better at the prediction
side of things in the sense that they um
rely less upon um
deep past experience and
assign more precision or um
more potency to um
the more recent evidence so they have a
different style of evidence accumulation
that enables and also they have the
right
level of uncertainty about what will
happen next so it looks as if
in their predictive engagement um
and epistemic foraging in that world it
looks as if they
are better at predicting changes
because they're not committed to a
particular uh a particular
um explanation or understanding of how
their world works
on the other hand if you
create a world which is incredibly
predictable
and learnable then over time
the natural pressure to minimize
um free energy um
translates into a pressure to minimize
complexity namely
a way of modeling your world
and your exchange with it in the
simplest way possible in accordance with
oklahoma's principle
and what that lens leads to is somebody
it sounds as if it's somebody who
becomes a subject matter expert
but so the subject matter is their lived
world that has now
become so predictable that they
do not entertain all possible other
outcomes because they have precise
beliefs about the way that things will
unfold and they can make very wise very
parsimonious or using parsimonious
degrees of freedom
they can make um they can make moves and
become very expert in the way that this
particular
non-volatile predictable i.e precise
world works and the link with aging here
is that
if you allow for the fact that we create
our own environments and your
many levels of active inference will um
permit or is a way of framing our
economic construction
what tends to you know what what people
the story people tend to tell
is that as you get older you basically
make your world more predictable and you
become a subject matter
expert in your own lived world so i like
the example i
i no longer go bungee jumping i'll go to
discos because my world is very very
predictable and
i you know very much an expertise
because my world is basically my
conservatory in my study and my bedroom
so
i i'm a complete ex subject expert on
that
you take me out on you know to disco and
i will not
i will not be able to predict what's
going to happen next because i'm old
whereas you know adolescents and
children and certainly
and you know newborn infants or newborn
artifacts discovering
their world which is full of uncertainty
and they are not yet subject experts and
and the epistemic pressures or
motivation for them to
learn about you know what happens if i
do that
and what can i control what can't i
control that will make them
very quickly into prediction experts
until they become
until they become sufficiently fluent
that they can now
um engineer their world to make it
non-volatile
and then they presumably will become
subject matter experts
so yeah i'm sure that would be that
would be
fairly simple to simulate using you know
all the
toy active inference schemes that we
currently
currently use and it would be really
interesting if
these two different kinds of synthetic
agents
did develop some cognitive styles and
confidence in what they were doing that
looked exactly like
the distinction you're talking about i'm
not sure it would work but if it does
that
that would be you know i think an
illuminating
proof of principle thanks for this
answer and for this session from the lab
and edu
that last answer really spoke to the
importance also of intergenerational
learning at this point we will take a
five minute break
and we will return for dot coms so
thanks again and we'll see everybody in
five minutes
right here